First T-virus malware in history
targeting
Iran's nuclear program.  It was just
proof that you can actually do damage to
software.
6-7 months have passed since we started and
then Enne tried the product and
started wanting it, right?  He didn't want to
give it back, but
exponential growth, maybe the following year,
a few tens of thousands of euros,
a few hundred, up to ok
million, 2 million 10. The
startup book says you have to aim for the IPO and
to get there you have to grow
significantly.  You can't just sit back and
grow your business organically
because others are playing that game.
We are still the only player in our
market that Espositi, that is, all the
others, are losing.
You may not know his name,
yet every government knows his
company.  He is Morano Carullo, born in 1982
and together with Andrea Ccano in 2013 he
founded Nozomi Networks which deals with
protecting the
most sensitive infrastructures of the
most powerful countries in the world from hackers.  Power grids,
airports, military facilities, even
the Super Bowl.  In short, it
deals with industrial cyber security and
starting from Italy, Nozomi has arrived
all the way to Silicon Valley, raising
over 260 million dollars, before
being acquired for 1 billion by
Mitsubishi in 2025, becoming one of the
largest investments in the world in
this sector.  And that's why I went to
Nozomi's headquarters in Switzerland to
talk to Moreno.  Let's start from his
educational background.  Well, I
basically started working when I was in
high school, when I was in the scientific high school,
with the computer, I played games and so on,
until I started developing.
Fifth grade, I
basically started working for a
technology publication,
right?  It combined a passion for
technology with a passion for
programming and the creation of systems.
What was a blog?  Hardware Upgrade, a
site dedicated precisely to technology and
there was already a bit of a challenge in
running a non-trivial infrastructure,
hardware and software for both the
CMS part that didn't exist, but above all
the forum, the concept of community was
the largest in Italy and so it was
quite a challenge, right?  So running
a series of Linux machines tuned
to support that load when VS didn't
exist,
which was the year
2000, I'd say. Let's say that then I understood
something, what I had understood a little
as a self-taught person about how to make
software, how to make these
systems, was absolutely not
enough to do something serious, of
quality and so from there I then
seriously enrolled in university, right?   Okay
.  And then I started working
part-time.
What did you study in your undergraduate degree?
Informatics.
Pure.  Yes, computer science, Varese, and I did my
master's degree with a focus on machine
learning when no
one else was doing it.  I was passionate about it, in short, I like
mathematics and then again after finishing the
specialist part he did a
doctorate, a doctorate that was
financed by an Italian company set
pixel.
How old were you when you finished the
whole course?  Even the doctorate?
late 2010, early 2011, then actually I
got married in 2009, so then I ended up having
a child and there in that environment my
wife kept urging me, "No, but
do something, make it up."  No, he saw me as
a bit limited until
Andrea arrived and at the same time he was doing
a PhD on cyber
security until he came and
said "But why don't we do that
thing?"  He was almost joking because
he said, "You have a son."  Another one is
coming your way, there was a second one right away, it was all
set, right?  And so from there we started
seeing each other basically every
Sunday, two computer scientists with the book
Business fan for Dammis basically
on the Sequoia website, Sequoia Capital
which was there, how do you write a business plan
to give a speech?  Okay, let's start from
there.  No.
How did you meet Andrea
at university?  He
wasn't particularly proficient in
business either.   In my opinion,
looking backwards, yes and
no.  Neither of us had ever started a business, but
in reality we were both children of
entrepreneurs, right?  We grew up
seeing our parents, our
family, have a business.
What kind of entrepreneurs?  Classic
Italian manufacturing,
right?  A small integrated system in the
Baresotto area.
So he's a computer scientist too,
I think.  Yes, in a different way, but
I've always seen, no, that kind
of thing.  I've always had a bit of a
hard time, but being
an entrepreneur is difficult, isn't it?  I saw him washing
a lot, etc. etc.  And then I
realized that, well, it's a bit more my
way, no, to push, to do
something.
To recap, Moreno and Andrea
met and started with the idea of
creating a company that would protect
industries from hackers.  They then
created software capable of mapping,
monitoring, and protecting all
factory assets, such as all
industrial machines
connected to the network, sensors,
highly sensitive documents, and industrial protocols.
But how did this very particular idea come about
?  It's a project funded by the
European Community where they were
asked, well, let's see if
this type of device is vulnerable?
The answer was yes.  And the other
interesting thing was that, let's say, the
most classic IT protection technologies
can be or do this
kind of thing, both for a
technological reason and then unlike IT,
if an email I was waiting for, well, I'll get
angry, who cares, they'll
send it to me, but if an F blocks a
critical command in a production site, that
's a problem.  problem for
human life and therefore the scale of values ​​is
totally different.   Okay
.  But how did
Moreno and Andrea actually leave?  The idea
was to provide a product that was
completely independent, capable of
showing what was happening on the
production site, precisely because
the first thing these asset owners didn't know was
what they had.  Yes, I have the
power generator, I have a part that performs a
certain type of oil refining process
, but exactly which
devices are there, how they are connected to each
other, what version of software is on them
was information that was a bit lost over
time because these systems were
perhaps created by different vendors, by
different companies that succeeded each other, but
the concept of documenting
exactly what was happening and why
was not a thing.  So the first thing
the product had to do was show what
a Setoner had and how the various
pieces, the various devices communicated
with each other, and so just
showing them what they had was a
way of opening their eyes a little.
So first thing we did was
visibility and second thing, once it
has visibility I'll show you if there
could be any problems.
Problems that can be caused
by humans or by actual
attacks.
In short, at the time, companies did not
perceive how
dangerous the cyber problem could be.  They were
more concerned with threats such as
military or physical ones.  However, there
was one case that opened
many people's eyes: the first time
hackers managed to
infiltrate and slow down a nuclear power plant
.  With Staxnake it was then the
first malware for T in history, a
malware targeted by the
Iranian nuclear program.  It was just
proof that damage can be done.
In that case, it was the centrifuges
of enrichment with
software that were sort of the moment
when they started to open their eyes.
With these premises, Nozomi
presented itself with an MVP that was a mix
between a software part and a
physical console to be sold to factories.  We
produce the software, but then it was - and still is -
sold in the form
of an appliance, a server, a
machine that you install in each
production site and you can connect
directly and see everything.
This has to be very simple to
set up, automatic, so it had to
be able to operate
very simply.
Ok, but how much time passed from
the conception of the business plan to
actually getting the first customer, namely
Enel?  The Sunday evening part to
make a business plan for a year, then we
left, Andrea had resigned from his
job in the summer of 2013, I
then finished in September.
6-7 months have passed since we started and
then Enne tried the
product and started wanting it, right?   He did
n't want to give it back to us anymore, did he?
When we took him to get tested.  In
reality, the first contract arrived
a few months later, a contract worth
a few billion euros, and we
scaled it.  Today he is certainly an
important customer.
Even though Nozomi has raised
hundreds of millions over the years, it started with
virtually no funding and therefore faced
considerable difficulties.
We started with little thanks to a
business angel Paolo Busani.  This
first phase was aimed at moving on
to the next one, so if you want the challenge, you can
easily manage to obtain
significant references.  The other thing
was that it seemed a bit like telling the
client that he needed the
flying car, and therefore a bit like trying to obtain
budgets that didn't exist.  People lived
under the assumption that the
physical separation of systems was sufficient to
protect them.  This thing has gotten a
little fake.  Little by little the systems have
become converted.
When the company was still small,
obviously it was possible to have just a
few people, but soon, to scale, the team
had to expand.
Now we are 150 and more we founded,
we brought on board a
very capable person.  Let's say that in this
first phase we hired less than 10
people.  With the first Angel business
we got to a certain point, but then
we started to have the first
slightly more institutional investor,
Lven helped us in particular
Giovanni Canetta, he believed in us a little,
no, in this adventure and pushed us,
if you like, towards the United States.
Flanven is a venture capital firm
founded by Giovanni Canetta and Rosario
Bifulco, whose main
investor is Carlo De Benedetti, a
legendary entrepreneur and former
CEO of Fiat and
Olivetti.  Planben's investments
also include Cronaca di
serraturatoio, a media company that they
acquired and then recently sold to
Will.  But going back to the video, with
the entry of the Nozomi fund, it is
now ready to move on to the
Silicon Valley championship
and there we can say that the numbers started
to change when the
American investors entered, we took on an
external investor, Edgar, we are still part
of the company today, we would have spent a year
working together a bit, it is important
that there is good chemistry, right?  these
things.  From there he then went blind with
Nozomi's transformation into an
American company in October.
But to make it internationally, it's not
enough to go to America.  What you
need are customers.
In 2016 the customers were European.  We've
reached the point where we need to
relaunch Nozomi, haven't we?  Because in the world
they were saying "But Nozomi who?"  It was
therefore a journey starting in 2016
where we began to bring
American customers on board, obviously in
parallel with all the other parts of the world.
While in the critical infrastructure space,
it is very likely that a
customer has a global presence,
so very quickly we find ourselves
being a global company with a presence in the
Middle East, Australia, Asia –
basically, pretty much everywhere.
Going international is one of the
most difficult challenges for
Italian companies.  For Nozomi, the key was
working with local enterprises so
that their products could be
used by all their divisions around the
world.  In fact, growth has
not stopped since then.
I would say that there was no exponential growth in 2013
, maybe the
following year a few tens of thousands of
euros, a few hundred up to ok
million 2 million.
But how important is it to close
a series 6 with good numbers, especially if
others follow?  When you do a
Series A, revenue only matters so much
.  The key thing that
then made us believe in investing was that
we have three significant clients in
three different parts of the world.
Clearly, the further you go with the
investment series, the higher your barrier to
entry becomes, right?  So how much is the
turnover etc.  Maybe it's not a question of whether I
invest or not, but it then becomes a question
of evaluation.
As the company grew year after
year, something unexpected happened:
Covid.  What impact did it have on
Nozomi?  which on the one hand makes software,
on the other sells it to industry.
From a product perspective, it
was, ironically, an event that
changed us because, until the pre-
Covid period, all critical infrastructure
essentially existed within a
separate, disconnected ecosystem, which
must be absolutely protected by
physical separation, but
from one day to the next, they found themselves having to
operate all their things remotely.
At that stage we decided to
invest in what later became known as the flagship
Vantage.  Such a crazy event,
negative in so many ways.  However, it was
something that transformed us,
that made us faster.
The last 20 years have seen
incredible technological changes, but
have the threats changed over time?  maybe a
little.  The fundamental concept is that
manufacturing companies, but also of
any kind, where there is
automation, need
devices, but in the end what they
do are specialized computers
that do only one thing and do it very
well, right?  It's a control loop that
runs a belt that spins
products and controls how much energy is
produced.  They are specialized computers
designed to optimize certain things.   It
must withstand certain
temperatures and humidity.  Whoever produced it
produced it with this kind of
mentality.  The fact is that first of all the
mentality with which they were produced is
a mentality from decades ago.
So even the aspect of what's
called product security is a little bit
low.  What is product security?  It's
how much a product can
withstand unexpected use of the
thing, right?  But if I send you commands,
packets, something unexpected,
you stand or fall.  Well, many times
you fall because it wasn't
planned, right?  The other factor is the fact
that being specialized and having to
withstand a series of
physical or environmental challenges they are less
powerful, so for this reason some
technological choices are dictated by
that.  Then something is changing, yes,
but not much, because these
devices have to be bought anyway, they remain
in operation for 20, 30, 40 years and the last
thing those who make these things work want to do
is compromise
production, right?  The way
these things are done makes it very
easy to have these flaws, these
vulnerabilities that attacks can then
sit on.
Okay, we've talked a lot about how
important cyber security is, but
what are the
most important cyber threats today?  We do
an analysis of what the threats are, of
their evolution over time,
where we go to describe what we
observe.  Ransware certainly
remains the number one threat, the
easiest thing that can be done
.  The second thing you see
is malware that
essentially discovers
industrial devices and sends
specific commands, right?  So they go and
disrupt the production.  When
an M is called Industroyer he has a
very very clear objective which is to
compromise the
operation of things.
Nowadays, hacker attacks
are increasingly frequent and affect
companies large and small.  These are cases
where it's obvious, no, I don't know, the hospital
is closed because there's been a
ransomware attack. Sometimes it's hidden,
but today with the
compliance regulations that exist in Europe it's
a bit difficult to do so, but there are still
many cases where they are
detected and stopped.  The slightly
more mature thing today is that we have
done everything that our
power can do by putting in place the technologies,
capable people with technological and
procedural controls, then if
something happens, if I have done everything I will have
my backup, my
redundant system, so I will be less inclined to
hide it.
At this point, since Nozomi will have a
significant database of how many times
companies and their customers are
attacked, I wondered: is there a
notable event in which one of their companies
defended itself thanks to Nozomi Networks?  We
make a solution, we sell a
solution, but we don't make it
work.  Our partners take care of this
so we can scale
globally.  That's right.  On some,
you know, maybe they see some things, maybe they
ask us directly, do you understand that
something happened?  By blocking one attack
at a time and amassing more and more
customers, the company grew
exponentially and raised many
investment rounds,
even reaching rounds and but why was
so much money needed and how was it
spent?  It must be said that each
market has its own maturation times.
Let's look at how fast
pure AI is growing, the market has
these characteristics and we go
through these stages to grow
the company.  The startup book says
you have to aim for the IPO and to get there you
have to grow significantly.  You can't just sit back
and let the company collapse
organically because others are playing
this game, the growth game,
the investment game.
It's a business like yours that
I imagine employs mostly technicians
and sales people.
Sales is certainly a
heavy part, sales is a heavy part of the
accounts, but to scale you don't just need to
hire people, you also need to have
good partners, you need to build a
network that then allows you to scale.
So to scale it
mainly deals with the technological part,
while for the sales part, that is,
actually selling the product, it has
a series of partners, distributors on whom
it relies to sell as much as possible.
The distributor acts partly as a bank,
partly as a warehouse, and then the second level
after the distributor is the partner who
then buys from the distributor,
sells it to the customer. They're not always
independent, so then maybe they turn
to us. We have professional services
that then support them in being successful,
but our goal is for them to
take care of it themselves.
And how did this system come about?
Direct contact with the customer is essential
because you need to understand if what you're
doing makes sense.  So the product
market is built a little day by
day.  At the beginning, it's super healthy to have a
direct relationship with customers.  At a certain
point he discovers nothing new anymore.
Well, that moment is the moment where
you need to start investing a little.
How many distributors do you have?  400-500
qualified, well-trained partners
worldwide.
At a certain point, Mitsubishi arrives
first with an investment round
aiming for 7% of the capital and then decides
to buy the entire company.
Why does this happen?
CS aimed to bring on board
strategic investors, which
could be industrial companies
that have a certain interest in having a
foot in this thing, no.  And one of
them was Mitsubishi.  Their goal,
well, to be both financial and to
have a presence, is an
important thing because today more or less all
the players of that caliber have something
or at least rely on some
technology and let's say that from that moment
until the moment where they decided to
make a leap forward,
a collaborative relationship was built, we
developed a product together and so
they probably understood that it could
be the right choice, right?  The
main road is always the IPO,
but one goes for everything, right?  An
opportunity arose, there
could have been some interest on both sides and today
we are here.
With his exit, Morano Carullo has
probably gone from 0 to 100, from a
likely normal net worth to a
net worth of tens of millions of euros.
In these cases, it's important to know how
to invest. Like many entrepreneurs I
've interviewed, such a significant exit
is great, but it's important to know how
to manage it.  And this applies to everyone,
because even those who don't want to make a
multi-million dollar exit, if they put aside a certain
amount every month for years, in a few
decades they can build up a
nest egg that could allow them to
retire.  I also recently made
an exit not for 1 billion, but for 10
million and I was ready,
already capable of investing.  In fact, I have been
investing with Trade Republic for some time now, for years now. I have been an
ambassador for Trade Republic for years
and I use it not only for
investing, but for everything.  There's a
free checking account, which I use to
buy stocks, bonds, commodities,
and much more.  The accumulating cards
have no additional costs and I
also use the card with safeback.  But one
of the best aspects is definitely
receiving interest on uninvested cash
.  Consider that for all new
users who sign up to Trade Republic
there is 3% interest on
uninvested liquidity.  This means that this
interest is calculated every day and
deposited every month.  If you had
€10,000 in uninvested cash, that
would be €300 per year divided by each
month.  To get it, just go
public with the link you find in the
description in the first comment or in the QR
code you want right now.  And don't
worry if you're already a user,
just invite other friends to
unlock the 3% too.  Last
year I made a video with Luca
Carabetta, the country manager of Trade
Republic in Italy, sharing with him the
questions, doubts, and criticisms
my users had about
Trader Republic.  Most of
them asked for better customer service
and this wish was
fulfilled with a 24/7 telephone customer service
and then more technical helpers
for whom Trade Republic was too
simple, Trade Republic thought
of them too.  Now from Desktop there is
a more complete interface, suitable for
more experienced traders, where orders
can be placed on more than 30 exchanges
and there is also a system for making
purchases where the stock costs less or,
conversely, selling it where it is
paid more, in short, reducing the
spread.  But these are technical things,
so let's go back to Moreno Carullo and
see how his story continues.   Do
you think the fact that Nozomi is a
Japanese word
means hope?  Well, I don't know if it
also means hope, but actually when
we were making the famous business plan
above the last thing we
wanted to put in it was the name, except that
in creating this thing we
often read the name of Palo Alto Networks in
Super Successful Company the head of
cyber and then I had my wedding day in
Japan, I saw the Nozo, no that was
fast and secure.  But what do you think, Nozomi Networks
?  Oh, nice.  And
what happened after the sale of the shares to Mitsubishi?  Well,
De Benedetti
will certainly have made an excellent exit with Plumven.  But how did it go for Moreno
?
Generally speaking, what an
acquirer does is not a pro-attitude, but
someone who acquires in a
total way, acquires everything.  Then it has
mechanisms for retention, it can
be delayed payments, which can be
incentives for a certain amount of time.
Okay, so what's next for
Moreno?  Will she create something new or
will she remain in Nozomi forever?  Life is
short, so I definitely want to
continue what you've done, but I
basically want to be a dad,
dedicating time to my family.  And
how many children do you have?
And four.  There are those who maybe
potentially you can do it full time if
Exactly.  There are those who, after one
fan like this, want to make another and
another.  It's not for me.  Well,
maybe I'll do something else to keep from
getting bored, but it's still exhausting, eh,
doing this kind of thing.
But what were the moments when
Moreno and his team had to
grit their teeth?  So, certainly
in the phase, let's say, we moved from the
business side Angela, to the
restructured investment side, we were
a little short on money, no, on
resources, so there we had to be a
little more careful than usual.
Even the pandemic, although it
had some positive effects, meant we had to
transform the company somewhat, whereas
before everything was about growth at all costs.
Value was simply given by
growth beyond efficiency.  After that,
even the way you grow
has become very important.  We are
still the only player in our
market that Espositi, that is, all the
others lose
money.
As always, there was a stage in the competition
where there were maybe up to 20
competitors. Today, just look at
Garner, in short, those who
remain can be counted on the fingers of one
hand.
There is no one who has put in
difficulty
in any environment, it is that thing that
lights up a little, a little spice and makes you
do better.  So if they hadn't caused
trouble we
probably wouldn't be here.
You've had some mentorship.
I'm not a person who idolizes
people.  I've certainly met
many who have allowed me to
learn some new concepts.  Then
into the world of Silicon Valley.   It was
certainly a great thing
to have access to these things and it
allowed us to avoid many mistakes.  I
stopped focusing on the person, I
like concepts more, right?  Something
that perhaps made a difference
in your past, you say "Come back,
shake my hand because I
did this, this one got it right".  If I look
back there are some episodes that were
certainly fundamental.  For
example, if I hadn't found myself married
with children and the desire to do more,
more, I wouldn't be here.  If I hadn't
had a PhD,
maybe in some contexts it would have been less
appealing.  It's something that others have done
, like Andrea.
Certainly the doctorate he did,
then went to work for an
oil company is very important.   There were
no major moments of
decision.
I like things that change little
over time, rather than
catastrophic ones, don't you?  that change
a lot, I'm allergic to the new
shiny object.  So when there is something
very new, very different, the first
reaction is an allergic one.
The advent of artificial intelligence
has turned our lives upside down, making us
feel exactly like we did when the internet
exploded in the early 2000s.
The idea of ​​automating everything and having
our own personal agent ready to
serve us and sometimes replace us is
truly crazy.  Yet not everyone
has embraced this idea with the same
enthusiasm.
Today AI means Gen AI.  Is
that okay?  it holds a lot of things underneath.   It
certainly has two components, one of which is what
is in our
products.  We use
this type of technology in our products to help
customers do more with less.  The other
component is in development.  I don't believe
in a world without humans making
software, but I do believe it's a suit of
armor everyone needs to have to
go faster.  There is an
impact today, probably the time
spent experimenting with these things
balances out the gain.
Probably when there is a bit of a
stabilization, more clearly, then
you remove that part of the investment and
there is an increase in productivity.
So is Moreno afraid of missing the
train if he doesn't use the EI or is he
calm like this?   Apart from that,
we certainly
use that in Ozomi.  I think you can do
everything like this.  Maybe not, he can certainly
do more with less.   Do
you think this
single Prenor who runs the Billion
Dollar Company without being a technician really exists?
It's possible, but it's really difficult on your own
because you need someone to
sell you this product, you need to
make yourself known, so you need
humans.  To date, there is no evidence that
software designed and evolved
entirely by AI has the same
qualitative characteristics, for better or
worse, as that made by humans.
Am I willing to bet on this?  No,
well, maybe a more complex software.
Is it still worth studying computer science or
would it be better to choose something else?  From those who
advise, for example, to go straight
to mathematics or physics.
There are some who say that we shouldn't
do computer science anymore, it's dead, I don't really
believe it.  You can't be everyone,
I'd say.  Follow your passion, avoid
getting into a sector that is already
more likely to be eaten up
by others.  These two pieces of advice here see
university programs being modified a little
, trying to channel
students better from this point of
view.  What is your routine like today?   I get up
quite early in the morning 6:15am
to get here early and
do things without distractions.
What time do you attack here?
7:30 am
before I wake up
and I function well like this, in the sense that I
tend to produce more at that time
of the day.
So you have to bring someone else to school with your children
.
Well, it means that yes, I have a family,
after all.  And then I use the morning to
do a series of activities together with
my teams, my teams here at the headquarters of
various types that could be meetings,
could be inspections, could be
reasoning, brainstorming, on new
products and technologies and then I
tend to leave the afternoon part
to those in the United States.
Something is appearing now in the morning too,
more Japan is visible, right?
maybe at 8:00 there is the meeting in Tokyo
maybe it happens but rarely to do the
cola 3 time zone, so maybe you have to
wake up the cola starts at 6:00 or
5:30 or one of the three has to
suffer substantially.
Talking to Moreno was really
cool, not only because he made
an amazing exit with an
amazing company, but also because it makes you realize
how many opportunities there are in the world.
He, for example, seized the opportunity
to combine manufacturing and the
economic heart of Italy with tech,
which was his background, managing to
create one of the few tech companies that
have made a splash in Italy and reached the
whole world.  Let me know if this
story inspired you, which
other entrepreneurs you'd like to see on the
channel, and if you missed them, check
out all the videos I've made with
amazing entrepreneurs at
amazing companies.